Finding Aid for Tailyour Family Papers
William L. Clements Library, University of Michigan
Tailyour family papers 1743-2003 1780-1840
Tailyour family papers
Tailyour family
12.75 linear feet
wclmss002057
The collection focuses primarily on John Tailyour, a Scottish merchant who traveled to North America and Jamaica in the 1770s and 1780s to conduct business, before finally returning to his home in Scotland in 1792. His correspondence is heavily business related, centering especially on his trading of slaves, foodstuffs, and sundry goods. It also chronicles the current events in both Jamaica and the Empire. Many of Tailyour's correspondents debate the meaning and merit of the cessation of the slave trade in the late 18th century, as well as the military events of the American and Haitian revolutions, and of the Maroon rebellion of 1795. The papers also include letters between John and his family in Scotland regarding John's mixed-race Jamaican children. He sent three of his children to Britain to be educated, which caused much family concern. Tailyour's account books and financial papers relate both to his Jamaican estate and business, and to his Scottish estate, from which he received added income from rents. The accounts for this estate continue for several decades after Tailyour’s death in 1815. A number of disparate and miscellaneous letters, war records, photographs, and realia that belonged to various members of the extended Tailyour family date mainly from the late-nineteenth and early-twentieth centuries.
William L. Clements Library, University of Michigan
2002, 2012. M-4207, M-4208, M-4936, M-4938.
The collection is open to research.
Previously owned by the Tailyour family before Clements Library acquisition.
Biography
John Tailyour was born to Robert and Jean (Carnegie) Tailyour on February 29, 1755, in Marykirk, Scotland. Robert sent young John to Glasgow to work as a clerk in the merchant firm of George McCall. In 1775, McCall helped John find employment in Virginia as a factor in the Glasgow-Virginia tobacco trade, but the chaos resulting from the onset of the Revolution forced John to leave for home. He returned to America two years later to trade between New York and the West Indies, but again returned to Glasgow one year later. In one last attempt to trade in the western Atlantic, Tailyour sailed for America in 1781, but was thwarted by Cornwallis' surrender at Yorktown just days before his arrival. However, Tailyour did find work supplying British prisoners of war in Pennsylvania, until American soldiers frustrated the deal. Fed up with the emerging independence of the American colonies, John left for Jamaica in 1782, encouraged by his cousin, Simon Taylor, one of the island's wealthiest inhabitants.
In Jamaica, John Tailyour quickly flourished under the supervision of his notable cousin. Originally acting as an attorney for absentee planters, John built up enough revenue to start his own merchant house, McBean, Ballantine and Taylor in 1784. He had altered the spelling of his last name to "Taylor," hoping to capitalize on his cousin's success. Tailyour's partner Peter Ballantine became one of his closest business associates and lifelong friend. The firm began trading in plantation supplies, dry goods, and various other commodities. However, the demand for slaves in the British West Indies impelled the firm to enter that trade, and they quickly became known for their efficiency in unloading and selling slaves. John's Glaswegian network helped him build a base of merchant contacts that facilitated his success. He soon became a popular advisor to other young Scottish traders, who wanted to try their fortunes in the Caribbean market.
In 1792, Tailyour reorganized his firm with James Fairlie and renamed it Taylor, Ballantine, and Fairlie. Later that year, however, John returned to Scotland for health reasons, and soon adapted to the life of an aristocrat. In 1793, he married George McCall's daughter Mary, with whom he had ten children. He repurchased his family's estate of Kirktonhill, began renting out nearby land in Marykirk, and sold off his interest in his colonial firm in 1797. His bad health continued to burden him until his death in 1815.
The topic of slavery is prevalent in this collection, as Tailyour was involved professionally and personally with slaves. During the last quarter of the eighteenth century, the greatest profits in the slave trade were made, and Tailyour's firm certainly benefited well. The era also witnessed the advent of arguments against the slave trade, and calls for its cessation. Tailyour was unapologetic in his support of the slave trade, and vehemently castigated the emerging abolitionists. All of Tailyour's contacts did likewise, because of their own involvement with the trade.
During the mid-1780s, John took Polly Graham, one of Simon Taylor's slaves, as a common-law wife. Together they had three or four children, during John's sojourn in Jamaica. In 1790, John appealed to Simon for the freedom of Polly and their children. Simon granted the request, and Tailyour sent three of them (James, John, and Catherine) to Britain to be educated, and to remove them from the prejudices of Jamaica. Two of those children, James and John, are recorded in some detail in the collection. James became a serviceman in the East India Company army, and John worked as a clerk in a London merchant house.
After John Tailyour's death, the family continued to live off the proceeds of the Kirktonhill estate, until it was sold in the early-twentieth century. A long string of Tailyour men undertook careers in the military from the mid-nineteenth to the twentieth century. Kenneth R. H. Tailyour became a high-ranking officer in the British military in the twentieth century. A number of photographs, diaries, and war records in this collection come from his family and professional experiences, as well as those of his brother, Ian Stewart, who also served in the military.
The Tailyour family papers are arranged in three series:
Series I: John Tailyour (1743-1815)
Sub-series 1: Correspondence
Letters
Letterbooks
Sub-series 2: Business Papers
Business papers
Account books
Series II: Tailyour Estate (post-1815)
Sub-series 1: Correspondence
Sub-series 2: Business Papers
Business papers
Account books
Sub-series 3: Hunting Papers
Series III: Tailyour Family (bulk post-1815)
Correspondence
Letterbooks
Account books
Military
Genealogy & Probate
Printed Materials
Illustrations, Artwork, and Poetry
Photographs
Ephemera
Realia
Audio-Visual
Miscellaneous
The collection has three substantial parts. The most comprehensive and cohesive section is the one concerning John Tailyour, until his death in 1815. The second part contains business papers and accounts related to the Tailyour estate. The third part is the least integrated, and consists of a variety of family papers, photographs, military memorabilia, and other miscellanea.
The Tailyour papers date from 1743 to 2003, with the majority of the collection concentrating in the period from 1780 to 1840. Within these bulk dates, are the two largest portions of the collection: the correspondence and accounts of John Tailyour until his death in 1815, and the account records of the Tailyour estate after 1815.
Seven boxes contain John Tailyour's personal and business correspondence of 3757 letters. The letters focus on Tailyour's mercantile activities in the Atlantic market, especially on the slave trade, its profitability, and the threat posed by abolitionists. Tailyour's correspondence also chronicles personal and family matters, including the education and provision for his mixed-race children from Jamaica. In addition, the collection contains four of Tailyour's letter books of 1116 copies of retained letters that cover the period from 1780 to 1810, with the exception of the years 1786-7 and 1793-1803. In these letters, Tailyour's focus is business, particularly as it relates to the slave trade, but he also includes personal messages to his friends and family.
Tailyour's business papers contain 32 loose account records, as well as five account books documenting the years between 1789-90 and 1798-1816. These primarily concern his Kingston and Scottish estates, including the expense accounts and balance sheets for each, as well as the finances of his merchant activities during the period. Finally, 38 documents of probate records for John Tailyour mainly relate to his landed estate.
The latter portion of collection within these bulk years (1815-1840) also contains correspondence and accounts, although the 228 letters are almost entirely concerned with business accounts. These focus on Tailyour's estate after his death, with John's brother Robert as the main correspondent. Additional materials include 1761 business papers that chronicle the finances of the estate, 11 account books, and 6 hunting books. The business letters and account books detail the estate's expense accounts and receipts, as well as the balances for their annual crops, salmon fishing business, and profits derived from the rents collected on their land. The hunting books contain descriptive accounts of the family's hunts and inventories of their hunting dogs.
The third, and final, part of the collection consists of Tailyour family records (bulk post-1815), including 49 letters from various family members in the late-nineteenth and early-twentieth centuries and five letterbooks, kept by Alexander Renny Tailyour and Thomas Renny Tailyour. 4 account books are also present kept by Alexander Renny Tailyour and others. Some of the records concern the First World War, including a group of prisoner-of-war records sent from Germany, and journals kept at home that detail news of the war, and daily domestic activities.
The family history documents include 64 genealogical records and 58 probate records. Many of the genealogical items are brief notes on family history, and sketches of the family tree, including a large family tree that spans several hundred years to the present day. The probate records contain one will from the late-nineteenth century, but are otherwise entirely concerned with John Tailyour's estate in the years immediately after his death.
Of the printed records, Memoirs of my Ancestors (1884), by Hardy McCall is a genealogy of the McCall family, and Tailyour's Marykirk and Kirktonhill's estates are described in two printed booklets, one of which is an advertisement for Kirktonhill's sale in the early-twentieth century. Other printed material includes 14 various newspaper clippings concerning the family over the years, and 12 miscellaneous items.
The illustrations, artwork, and poetry comprise 14 fashion engravings, 12 sailing illustrations, a picture of a hunting cabin, two silhouettes, and a royal sketch, all of which date from the early- to mid-nineteenth century. Kenneth R. H. Tailyour's sketches are represented in two sketch books created in his younger years (1917 and 1920). Loose records of poetry, as well as a book of poems from George Taylor, are in this section.
The 221 photographs are of the Tailyour family from the late-nineteenth to the twentieth century, with the majority falling in the early decades of the twentieth century. Most are portraits of the Tailyour family from the early twentieth century, particularly Kenneth R. H. Tailyour.
The 138 pieces of ephemera are, for the most part, postcards of foxhunts during the nineteenth century. These announce the almost-weekly family foxhunts during the middle years of the nineteenth century. The 19 items of realia, include Robert Taylor's quill pen from 1826.
The audio-visual portion of the collection contains three items: a compact disc with an audio interview of John Dann, Director of the Clements Library, on National Public Radio's "The Todd Mundt Show;" a compact disc with photos of the West Indies; and a collection of photographs of the Tailyour papers in their uncatalogued state, and of the festivities surrounding the acquisition of the collection.
Finally, miscellaneous material of 18 pieces includes Robert Taylor's commonplace book of short stories, letters, and poems; the catalogue of Robert Taylor's books; James Tailyour's 1771 style and form book; and a communion book.
Subjects:
Scots--Jamaica--History--18th century.; Scots--Jamaica--History--19th century.; Slavery--Jamaica--History.; Slave trade--Jamaica--History.; Slaves--Emancipation--Jamaica--History.; Plantation life--Jamaica--History.; Jamaica--Race relations--History.; Merchants--Scotland--History.; Scotland--Commerce--History.; United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783.; Haiti--History--Revolution, 1791-1804.; Jamaica--History--Maroon War, 1795-1796.; Racially mixed people--Jamaica--History.; Atlantic salmon fishing--Scotland.; Fox hunting--Scotland.; Hunting dogs--Scotland.; World War, 1914-1918--Prisoners and prisons, German.; World War, 1914-1918--United States.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Tailyour family.; Tailyour, Ada.; Tailyour, George H.F.; Tailyour, George Robert.; Tailyour, Ian Stewart.; Tailyour, Joan.; Tailyour, Kenneth R.H.; Tailyour, Norman Hastings.; Tailyour, William Gordon.; Fashion prints.; Wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons.; Sailing ships.
Contributors:
Anderson, Alex.; Anderson, John.; Ballantine, Peter.; Dick, David.; Fairlie, James.; McCall, George, d. 1810.; McCall, John.; Renny, Thomas, d. 1799.; Tailyour, Ada.; Tailyour, Alexander Renny, 1775-1849.; Tailyour, George.; Tailyour, George H. F.; Tailyour, George Robert, b. 1805.; Tailyour, Ian Stewart.; Tailyour, James.; Tailyour, Joan.; Tailyour, John, 1755-1815.; Tailyour, Kenneth R. H.; Tailyour, Mrs. H.; Tailyour, Norman Hastings.; Tailyour, Robert.; Tailyour, Thomas Renny, 1812-1885.; Tailyour, William Gordon.; Taylor, George.; Taylor, James, b. 1786.; Taylor, Robert.; Taylor, Simon, 1740-1815.
Genre Terms:
Account books.; Birth records.; Clippings (information artifacts); Commonplace books.; Compact discs.; Death records.; Diaries.; Engravings (prints); Genealogies.; Journals (accounts); Letter books.; Marriage records.; Menus.; Military commissions.; Photographs.; Poetry.; Postage stamps.; Postcards.; Ration books.; Receipts (financial records); Recipes.; Scrapbooks.; Silhouettes.; Sketchbooks.; Vouchers.
- John Tailyour (1743-1815)
  - Correspondence
    - Letters
      John Tailyour received 3,757 letters. Most of them concern his business transactions in Jamaica and Scotland. His primary business partners were John and Alex Anderson, Peter Ballantine, David Dick, James Fairlie, George and John McCall, Thomas Renny, and Robert and Simon Taylor. Many of these contacts, including the Andersons, George McCall, and Robert Taylor, stayed in Britain. The Andersons took a particular interest in the slave trade. As a merchant in the American trade, George McCall often sought Tailyour's advice on the markets there, and discussed his own struggles with business after the war. He also served as one of Tailyour's early advisors, as Tailyour began his mercantile career under McCall's tutelage. However, by the 1790s, McCall was asking for Tailyour's advice, as he sought out business positions in Jamaica through John Tailyour's contacts. Eventually McCall's son John became one of Tailyour's clerks in Jamaica.
      The correspondence from John McCall, and from David Dick, Tailyour's other clerk, provides some of the most complete information on Tailyour's business and family in Jamaica, after he returned to Scotland. McCall, in particular, often visited Tailyour's Jamaican wife and children, in order to send him reports. Beginning about 1800, the content of McCall's and Dick's letters centered more around their dissolving business partnership. Both men appealed to Tailyour and his cousin Simon for support and arbitration, but the issue of dissolution was settled without them.
      Peter Ballantine and James Fairlie were John Tailyour's business partners in Jamaica, and both are an additional source of information on Tailyour's colonial interests after he returned to Britain. Unfortunately, their correspondence begins the year that Tailyour left for Britain (1792), so they offer little information about the founding of their firm, Taylor, Ballantine and Fairlie. However, both Ballantine and Fairlie kept Tailyour advised on the slave, sugar, and dry goods markets, while Tailyour still owned his interest in the Jamaican firm during the 1790s. They, and others, also wrote about events that occurred in the West Indies during the 1780s and 1790s, particularly as they affected the firm's business. They regularly mentioned their concern over the Revolution in St. Domingue in the 1790s, as well as the uprising of the Maroons in 1795, as both events threatened the social stability of Jamaica and its business climate. Ballantine and Fairlie discussed personal information throughout their correspondence, and, once Tailyour sold his interest in the firm, their remarks about family and personal matters became more frequent.
      As evidence of the strong ties between personal networks and business, Tailyour's brother Robert and his cousin Simon intermixed both personal and business information in their letters to Tailyour. Between 1788 and 1807, both were continually concerned about the possibility of the abolition of the slave trade. Simon also relayed his business orders to Tailyour, who still carried out work for his cousin during his stay in Jamaica. Robert, with his contacts in the East Indies, provided information on the markets there. His letters contain some of the most detailed information on the issue of Tailyour's mixed race children, including descriptions of the two boys. It was Robert who found schools for the children, as well as professions. A number of letters from the two boys, James and John, are included in the collection. James's correspondence is almost entirely centered on his entrance into the East-India Company army, as well as his initial struggles on the subcontinent after his arrival. John, who worked as a clerk, wrote about his future prospects outside the counting house, and his inability to live on his budget.
      Tailyour's mother, Jean, wrote several letters, expressing her concerns about her son's colonial family, and about his future plans for returning to Britain. Tailyour's extended family wrote some of the letters, including the Carnegies (his mother's family), and the Foulertons -- Tailyour's sister Catherine married a Foulerton. Tailyour's connections through the Carnegies and Foulertons, helped him to win a spot in the East India Company army for his son. In return, he helped connect several Carnegies in Jamaica, and gave financial support and advice to the Foulertons.
      - Adam, William, 15 October 1806-1 March 1811, 6 items (Box 1)
      - Adam & Mathie, 2 November 1796, 1 item
      - Adams, George W., 19 January 1804, 1 item
      - Allan, Robert, 29 March 1800, 1 item
      - Anderson, Alex, 2 November 1793-7 October 1796, 3 items
      - Anderson, James, 19 July 1798, 1 items
      - Anderson, John & Alex, 28 April 1794-17 May 1798, 62 items
      - Anderson, John, 4 May 1793-20 August 1795, 3 items
      - Arbuthnott, Ld, 6 February 1798-25 December 1810, 7 items
      - Arcedeckne, Chaloner, 6 February 1796, 1 item
      - Badenach, James, 14 November 1802, 1 item
      - Baillie, John, 5 May 1802-12 May 1802, 2 items
      - Ballantine, John, 6 July 1793-21 July 1798, 12 items
      - Ballantine, Peter, 16 September 1792-28 July 1805, 130
      - Ballantine, Peter, 27 October 1805-13 May 1810, 43 items (Box 2)
      - Barbour, Robert, 6 February 1796-20 February 1796, 2 items
      - Barnett, John, 9 December 1803, 1 item
      - James Bell & Co., 5 March 1810-10 March 1810, 2 items
      - Bingley, Thomas, 2 July 1795-7 November 1797, 4 items
      - Bingley, Pitt & Bingley, 26 April 1794-1 January 1796, 30 items
      - Bingley, Pitt & Maslen, 18 February 1795-14 December 1796, 13 items
      - Bisset, Andrew, 16 September 1802, 1 item
      - Blair, David, 30 July 1793, 1 item
      - Blair, Peter, 7 May 1792, 1 item
      - Blane, Thomas, 2 August 1793-2 August 1794, 2 items
      - Bowman, John, 14 April 1793-14 November 1809, 11 items
      - Brand, John, 11 October 1794-26 October 1815, 29 items
      - Brodie, 21 November 1806-15 January 1810, 2 items
      - Brown, David, 5 March 1792, 1 item
      - Brown, John, 16 February 1809-31 October 1810, 4 items
      - Brown, Thomas, 13 February 1795, 1 item
      - Brunton, Thomas, 30 December 1799-20 January 1800, 3 items
      - Burn, James, 30 November 1799-25 October 1800, 5 items
      - Burn, R, 13 August 1800, 1 item
      - Burn, Robert, 22 December 1799-26 December 1800, 5 items
      - Burnett, Al, 17 April 1797-22 November 1800, 5 items
      - Burnett, John, 6 January 1800-16 December 1806, 59 items
      - Burnett, Robert, 16 May 1806-23 November 1809, 16 items (Box 3)
      - Burnett, Colonel William, 7 May 1793-8 July 1811, 26 items
      - Camden, Calvert & King, 14 May 1795, 1 item
      - Campbell, John, 12 August 1791-26 July 1792, 2 items
      - Carnegie, Miss A, 12 March 1811, 1 item
      - Carnegie, Lady A.M., 28 August 1805-3 October 1811, 9 items
      - Carnegie, Sir David, 9 June 1794-3 March 1805, 24 items
      - Carnegie, George, 17 May 1790-15 December 1810, 14 items
      - Carnegie, James, 12 June 1800-14 December 1806, 12 items
      - Carnegie, Colonel John, 3 May 1805-October 1811, 8 items
      - Carnegie, Susan, 10 October 1809-17 December 1809, 3 items
      - Carnegie, Thomas, 25 March 1800, 1 item
      - Chandler, Thomas, 16 April 1811, 1 item
      - Christian, Peter, 10 January 1805-8 March 1805, 3 items
      - Christie, Alexander, 12 January 1793-26 October 1793, 5 items
      - Clarke, Robert, 15 November 1815, 1 item
      - Clarke, Thomas, 17 February 1794-24 June 1794, 4 items
      - Collons, William, 20 January 1794-24 March 1794, 3 items
      - Colquhoun, Lud, 12 February 1805-19 October 1806, 7 items
      - Colvill, William, 17 October 1805, 1 item
      - Corrie, Edgar, 31 July 1793-21 August 1806, 16 items
      - Cratenlong, Robert, 20 December 1798, 1 item
      - Crombie, Alexander, 1 May 1804-27 July 1811, 13 items
      - Dauney, Al, 16 February 1806-12 August 1807, 2 items (Box 4)
      - Dick, David, 14 August 1792-14 May 1811, 91 items
      - Dick, Hugh, 1 April 1796, 1 item
      - Dick, James, 10 January 1795-10 September 1797, 8 items
      - Dickson & Co., 31 January 1800-29 September 1811, 9 items
      - Dickson, Robt., 7 May 1800-13 August 1800, 3 items
      - Dodds, John, 10 August 1805, 1 item
      - Donnell, Joseph, 7 March 1794-3 August 1806, 10 items
      - Duff, R.H., 22 November 1806, 1 item
      - Duncan, Andrew, 23 September 1810-6 August 1815, 3 items
      - Dunlop, George, 25 September 1807-25 May 1808, 2 items
      - Duthie, James, 27 June 1801, 1 item
      - Earle, Thomas William, 2 November 1793-3 November 1794, 8 items
      - Elemer, Charles, 30 January 1798, 1 item
      - Fairlie, James, 16 September 1792-11 March 1811, 59 items
      - Fairlie, Mungo, 26 July 1796-20 March 1809, 12 items (Box 5)
      - Farquhar, James, 26 December 1803-12 August 1811, 7 items
      - Farquar, William, 19 June 1793, 1 item
      - Fearns, James, 8 May 1795, 1 item
      - Fearns, Murdock, 5 December 1793-10 June 1795, 3 items
      - Ferguson, James, 3 January 1811, 1 item
      - Fisher, Ralph, 6 January 1794-20 February 1794, 3 items
      - Fleming, John, 28 April 1806-13 September 1810, 3 items
      - Fleming, William, 18 May 1804-28 October 1806, 3 items
      - Fletcher, Thomas, 8 July 1811, 1 item
      - Forbes, William, 8 June 1793-1 December 1810, 6 items
      - Forrester, Robert, 8 June 1801, 1 item
      - Foulerton, Catherine, 21 September 1795-25 September 1811, 46 items